[Music]
Stanford
University I have gotten into the
pattern and I like the pattern of first
starting uh a lecture with a couple of
preliminaries sometimes they're
reminders sometimes they're new things
by now I've taught so many things so
many times that um although I may
remember that they're reminders you may
think they're new
things but
uh well I suppose one of the things we
ought to go over really quickly really
really quickly is the harmonic
oscillator and I will do that
exceedingly fast but the other thing I
wanted to go over before we begin is the
spin of massless particles the spin of
massless particles is a little bit
different in some ways than the spin of
massive particles
the basic difference is that massless
particles can never be brought to rest
they move with a speed of light and if
you slow them down they still move with
the speed of light and if you slow them
down more they still move with the speed
of light whereas particles with mass you
can truly slow down and bring them to
rest and that makes a difference in um
in certain properties about spin uh what
should we do first spin or well let's do
harmonic oscillator first to get it out
of the way uh very
quickly you know it all I'm just going
to just to set the uh the notation
mostly to get the notation consistent
I'll just go over it with you again uh
the energy or the lran of a harmonic
oscillator
is X do squared and then for reasons
that um if you go back in your notes
about the IC oscillators that describe
the oscillations of strings first of all
they had a little index n which which um
had to do
with remember there were cosiness cosine
n Sigma it was the N of that cosign how
many oscillations uh uh how
many oscillations over the interval
from0 to Pi the string makes so there
are those exob bends are the coordinates
that describing various kinds of
oscillations that was there and
for reasons that have no special depth
to them it turned out there was a four
in the denominator
here that was the kinetic energy and
then the potential
energy uh if I want to write the energy
I put a plus sign there the potential
energy was proportional to
x^2 same thing X subn squared it looks
like we've uh somebody
didn't do
their there was an x subn
2 divided also by four and then in
sitting in front is the square of the
frequency of the
oscillator and that was actually just n
sared that's what we got for the energy
of the in mode of
oscillation X do squ and it's a harmonic
oscillator kinetic energy plus potential
energy that's the LR that's H that's the
energy call it
e the
lran is
x.n square you know I'm going to stop
writing
n but remember I'm talking about x sub n
is x do^ 2 minus n 2 x^2 over 4 that's
lunian from this you can work out lr's
equations of motion and you can discover
that the oscillator oscillates with
frequency n okay uh let's next go to the
hamiltonian we want to do quantum
mechanics the way to go to Quantum
Mechanics is to First construct the
hamiltonian and then do some tricks with
it let's first construct the hamiltonian
I'll remind you oops this is over four
somebody should have corrected me you
all fail uh x do^ s 4 okay so what do
you do the first thing you do what's the
first step in constructing hamiltonians
the first step is to replace the X dots
by the
momenta the momenta P so if you remember
the derivative of lran with respect to
the velocity is called the momentum so
in this case with this particular factor
of four here here the momentum would be
X do / 2 why because when I
differentiate with respect to x dot I
get a two that cancels a two in the
denominator leaves a two there all right
that's the first step next step is you
rewrite the
energy in terms of instead of X dots you
use PS so we just have to solve for x
dot and plug it in in here what does
that give us that gives us let's see x
do^ 2 will be 4 p^2 / 4 so this will be
p^ S with no
four and
then potential energy doesn't change
plus
n^2 x^2 over
4 and that we now call the hamiltonian
h the quantum mechanical hamiltonian is
exactly the
same except that it becomes an operator
an operator in the space of States okay
now the trick is always the same for
harmonic oscillators let's just erase
all of this this could have been our
starting point right
here you look at this it's the sum of
squares a 2 + b
2 you write that a 2 + b 2 a 2 minus b^
2 is what it's a + b * a minus B how
about a 2 plus a s + b
2 that's a +
I * Aus
I work it out you get an a^ 2 minus I *
plus I is plus so you get plus b^ 2 and
the cross term goes away so you look at
this it's a sum of
squares and you rewrite it it's sum of
squares n what's what is this term a
square of this term is a square of NX
over2 right all right so we write that
this is
nx/
2 plus
IP *
nx/ 2 minus
IP that's the
hamiltonian okay next
step you give these two things names but
not quite first
let's think about the commutation
relations between these
two of course one of these is
essentially the creation operator or the
raising operator the other one is
essentially the the lowering operator
but we have to figure out which is which
and the numerical coefficients in order
to make them creation Annihilation
operators I'll just put over here for
your um to remind you the commutation
relations between annihilation operators
let's call them a minus and creation
operators A+ A+ when it acts raises the
energy by one
unit uh a minus lowers the energy by one
unit this commutation relation is just
one so that's how we identify creation
and and Annihilation operators they're
operators which are complex conjugates
of each other these two are complex
conjugates of each other and their
commutation relation is one
so let's work out the commutation
relations between
these and just check if we get one we
won't get one all right what's the
commutation relation between X and P do
you remember the commutator between X
and
P anybody
remember I'm setting H bar to
one what else besides H
bar
I go back and uh try to remember why
that's true XP minus PX is I all right
now here we have X we have a commutator
of n /
2 A minus I times the commutator of X
and P so let's first oh first of all
what about the commutator between this
and
this that's zero because everything
anything commutes with itself likewise p
with P the only terms are the cross
terms terms x with p and p with X all
right so if we just look at the first
term here or the cross term
here that will give us n
/2 it'll give us a minus I from here but
then the commutator of X with p is plus
I so that gets multiplied by plus
I all together makes it just n / two so
far that's the commutator of this guy
with that one how about this one with
this one again I see an I see an N over2
I see an I but now I have the PS and the
x's in the opposite order the result is
exactly the same thing just double
it so this one and this one give you the
same thing it just doubles all of this
just gives us
n now I wanted to get one but I got
n what do I do with it I just divide
both equations both of these operators
by the square root of n in other words
let's divide each of these by the square
root of
n likewise over here one over the square
N and that now eats up this n
here and that's the way to remember it
if you're on a desert island and you
can't remember what combination of x's
and
PS are creation and Annihilation
operators compared with over
here this is in this is one now okay if
I had my creation and Annihilation
operators interchanged I would get minus
one so we then
identify the annihilation operator a
minus is 1 over the < TK of n that means
Square < TK of n x /
2 plus I over the < TK n
p and the creation
operator is the same
thing except with a minus
sign I just do that to remind
you your creation and Annihilation
operators the creation operators
increase the energy by one unit and when
I say one unit I now mean one unit the
frequency of this oscillator is n
oops n units little n
units which n well it depends on which
xn I'm talking about we can now put in
we can now put back our
ins there's a creation operator and an
Annihilation operator for each
oscillation for each possible
oscillation of the
string and the frequency is
n the frequency of course is the amount
of energy that's added by exciting the
oscillator once so so we can work out
then uh what the energies are what the
energy spectrum
is and do the quantum mechanics of the
oscillators and that's basically the
spectrum of these strings now we'll come
back to it in a minute the other thing
to remember that I talked about last
time was if we're talking about
strings
in the realistic number of dimensions of
space and time namely three dimensions
of space one dimension of time good old
ordinary
space and we think about the string
moving with a great deal of momentum
down the z-axis then there are really
only two dimensions of oscillation to
take into account another time maybe
even later today I'll talk about the the
third direction of oscillation and how
it's determined by the others but the
independent degrees of freedom are the
oscillations in the plane of somebody
watching the string going down the
z-axis and so how many oscillations are
there Al together well there are
oscillations along the along the x- axis
that one Z down that direction Z all
right right toward U is X toward the
ceiling is
y uh the oscillations can occur in the X
Direction they can occur in the y
direction so that means that there's
another term I really didn't write the
full hamiltonian here I should have
written plus another term where X is
interchanged with Y exactly the same
that means for each frequency there will
be two oscillators the oscillator for
oscillations along the x- axis and
oscillations along the Y AIS let's give
them names let's call them a for the x-
axis and B for the Y AIS same equations
B minus
B+ equal
1 and same equations here except we'll
substitute for a we'll put B and
wherever I see X I will put Y what about
Q what about P sorry what about p p of
yeah there piece of X and piece of Y the
momentum in the X Direction and the
momentum in the y direction I won't
bother writing it
down all right from this equation here
and let's but let us put in the little
symbol n
here also goes
here let's solve this equation for
xn is two equations for let's think of
them as two equations for two knowns X
and
P how can I solve this to find out what
x is in terms of the creation and
Annihilation operator this is something
we'll use later I'm not sure we'll use
it tonight or
not but what I want to write is the
coordinate position of the string in
terms of the creation and Annihilation
operators that will turn out to be quite
useful so let's do
it this is easy if I want to isolate
X I want to get rid of
P that's easy just add these two
equations this term will
cancel so what do we get we get
A+ plus a minus and we should put a
little index n here for the nth
oscillation that's equal to N I think
it's just n square root of
n sorry n uh square root of
n time
xn square root of
xn square
root so we simply find the nth
coordinate is just the sum of creation
and Annihilation
operators divided by square root of n
real
easy it's just the square root of n that
you got to
remember now let's before
we leave the harmonic oscillator let's
just remember where these oscillators
came from they came from writing X of
Sigma remember what x of Sigma was oh
there's another one similar to it Y
subn is equal to B subn plus plus B subn
minus over < TK of n same thing
incidentally as I'm sure most of you
have heard the rumor that string theory
doesn't work very well when there are
only three dimensions of
space and I can confirm that rumor
tonight we need more Dimensions to add
more Dimensions we just add more
coordinates fortunately and now you keep
adding coordinates until you run out of
coordinates so it's that's the reason
incidentally that string theory is in 26
Dimensions they
actually
actually yeah okay never
mind all right remember what x of Sigma
was X of Sigma and Y of
Sigma we have a string moving around in
the XY plane looking at it moving down
the axis it has n's and along the string
we invent a parameter called
Sigma Sigma goes from 0 to
PI right
and and if we take any point on the
string it's characterized by a sigma
it's the sigth point if you like and it
has a particular value of X and Y here's
the XY axis each point on the string has
a definite location we call them X of
Sigma and Y of Sigma and we use our
freedom to Foria expand X and Y and we
find we write that this is the sum of a
n of cosine of n
Sigma times let's call it X subn and
what is X subn x subn is simply the fora
coefficient of the nth cosine wave in
the fora expansion of X and likewise
with
Y why did I use cosiness and not SS does
anybody
remember the boundary conditions are
such that the derivatives of X should
vanish at the end points that's the
condition that the force at the ends not
be so strong enough to cause infinite
acceleration but this is the right way
to expand the X's likewise with the
Y's summation
n y sub n cosine n Sigma and now we can
write these coordinates in terms of
creation and Annihilation
operators we can write them as the sum
of a
n of a plus of n plus a minus of n over
theare < TK of n time cosine n Sigma and
the same thing down here with
B's B subn blah blah blah
why is that interesting well the best
way to manipulate the quantum mechanics
of harmonic oscillators is through the
creation and Annihilation operators if
you want to find out what a particular
operator does to a Quantum State you
apply the operator but if you apply it
in the form of creation and Annihilation
operators you immediately see what it
does increases the energy decreases the
energy and that of course will be very
useful
but for the moment they're just
equations that I'm writing down in the
Blackboard uh because we'll use them
okay I won't go through these again
so if there are questions about them ask
them right
now I don't want you to ask me
philosophical questions about the
meaning of life the x of N is a function
also of Sigma no no no xmn are the Foria
series coefficients all of the sigma
dependences here
this is the sigma
dependence what do the xns depend on
though time time this time in this
infinite momentum frame which we gave a
name to we called it
TOA when I write Dots Dots always refer
to the time in this non-relativistic
analogy which I didn't call T because I
didn't want to confuse it uh with time
in the rest frame so I called it the
last time I believe I called it
too that means that every point on the
string is not just a function of Sigma
it is also a function of
to it's the xns which are dependent on
too why are they dependent on Tao
because they're oscillators they
oscillate they vibrate the xns vibrate
with oscillations they depend on time
the cosiness of sigmas those are the
ones which depend on
Sigma okay are there any other questions
yes two quick questions for you aren't
those for the creation uh
distraction operators aren't they
reversed in other words you get
subtracting energy from from A+ and no
you you add energy with A+ unless I'm
unless somewh along the line I uh I I
think I got it right we could we could
check it out but
uh why do you think you subtract
energy why what makes you think so well
I mean it's a negative you're decreasing
the value of what of A+ of what of
A+ how can you see any how can you see
what how can you look at that and see
which way you may be right but how can
you look at it and see I don't think
you're right but uh I'll check we'll
check in a minute but uh let's see um I
think he's thinking of it as a a real
number instead of as a complex number I
don't care if a real number or complex
number I still don't see how you could
look at it easily and see which one
raises the energy and which one lowers
the
energy he's just seeing the minus sign
and thinking oh you're looking at this
minus
sign that doesn't tell
you you have to go through the quantum
mechanics and you have to check whether
the commutation relations give you a one
or a minus
one and I think I did
that so no that this minus sign doesn't
tell you anything well it tells you
something but uh
not
okay
next and that's that's purely by way of
absolute review now what may oh oh oh oh
okay so how much energy well all right I
think I I think I said what I had to say
next question next preliminary the spin
of massless and massive
particles how
many
components or let's say states does a
system of spin J
have let's start with spin zero how many
states 2 one right 2J plus one
all right
so spin J has 2 J + one States spin zero
has one state spin one right so spin
zero
spin okay spin
zero one state spin one three states
spin two five states and so forth
however massless particles are special
they don't fall into this
category a massless spin zero state only
has one state but a massless spin one
state has two states not three a
massless spin two State system has two
states not five a massless spin three
two states the only one which is the
exceptional sort of odd man out is the
uh is the spin zero has only one state
all others have two
states for massless for
massless how do we understand that how
can that be question is how can it be
consistent how can it be consistent I
will tell you what the two states are in
every case
here yeah the particle imagine it moving
along a certain axis for the moment it
could be massless or massive and let's
suppose it's moving along a certain
axis let me consider the component of
spin along that axis what's the maximum
that let's forget spin zero here that
only has one state but let's go to spin
one what's the maximum spin along any
given
axis well the answer is the spins along
any axis can be 1 0 and minus one how
about spin
two 2 1 0 -1 and
-2 okay in each case there is always a
maximum spin in this case a maximum and
a minimum meaning to say uh maximum
positive and a minimum which would be
negative okay those can be thought of as
a states where the spin is maximally
along the direction of motion or maximum
opposed to the uh direction of motion
now as far as whether the spin is along
the direction of motion or against the
direction of motion that's really an
arbitrary choice of right hand versus
leftand
rule spin has to do with
rotation
momentum is a vector along an
axis my right hand my finger fingers
curl right-handed my left hand they curl
left-handed a spin that way is
considered positive along the uh along
the axis and a spin that way is
considered negative along the same axis
well simple reflection
symmetry tells you if you have one you
better have the
other if you have a right hand and
you're in a world with reflection
symmetry you will have a left hand if
there's a right-handed particle that can
spin that way there'll be a left-handed
one that can spin the other
way so if you have a particle moving
down the axis with the maximum component
of spin there must be another
possibility the particle must also be
capable of having the opposite namely
the minimum component of spin but is
there any reason why it has to have
spins in between so let's take the spin
one case the spin one case the three
states along that axis have spin one
zero and minus one those are the three
states we see because of reflection
invariance that if it has a spin one
along the axis it must also have a spin
minus
one must it also have a spin
zero well the an uh a z component of
spin a z component of spin along that
axis and the answer as I said depends on
whether the particle is massive or
massless so let me show you
why supposing the particle is massive to
begin with and supposing it has let me
let me argue that there must be three
states uh that it has if it's moving
down the
z-axis and it has spin along the the
axis so it's rotating this
way now imagine bringing that particle
to rest or better yet moving in such a
way that you keep up with a particle
it's not moving with a speed of light
it's got a mass you keep up with it and
you look at the particle and the
particle's at rest okay the particle is
at rest so
now you've discovered that there's a
particle at
rest
but moving along with it doesn't change
its spin if it's rotating this way and
going down that axis and you keep up
with it it will still be rotating that
way so it still has spin one along this
axis it has spin one along this axis but
now that you've brought it to rest you
can rotate
it and then boost it back
up and in that case you've created a
particle which is neither spinning
about which is neither has maximal spin
in that direction or minimum spin in
that direction but which is now has spin
pointing out of the Blackboard even
though the particle is moving down that
direction and you did that by first of
all bringing the particle to rest and
then saying if you're living in a world
with rotation
invariance if there's a particle at rest
whose spin is pointing along that axis
it must also be possible to have it
pointing along that
axis another way to think about
it is you could imagine after having
brought it to rest boosting it along the
perpendicular axis either way you wind
up with a particle whose spin is
perpendicular to the axis of motion and
that must be the case because you can
bring a particle to rest and then
accelerate it in a perpendicular
Direction without changing its spin okay
so
conclusion uh if you have a massive
particle it must have all three
states spin along that axis spin along
that axis and that's not enough you have
to be able to make up spin along the
perpendicular axis on the other hand if
the particle is massless there is
nothing you can do to bring it to
rest any Lorent transformation will
leave it moving with the speed of
light you cannot bring it to rest and
then rotate out from under the spin and
uh and boost it in another
Direction the implication is that if
particles have zero mass then it's
perfectly consistent that all they have
is maximal Spin and minimal Spin and
nothing in between that's typically the
case now you know this in another guise
for the
photon what guise is it for the
photon the
polarization of light the polarization
of light can be described in a number of
ways it can be
described as linear polarization
circular polarization but if you
describe it in terms of circular
polarization circular polarization in L
corresponds to
photons depending on whether the
circular polarization is right-handed or
left-handed it corresponds to an
assemblage of photons which are either
right hand spinning or leftand
spinning
um there are no photons which are not
polarized at
all polarization is always perpendicular
to the direction of motion it's either
right handed or left left-handed now
what about linear
polarization there's linear polarization
and I'm going to tell you now what
linear polarization is a linear
polarization if you
have linear
polarization is not zero angular
momentum along the direction of motion
it's a Quantum superposition of the two
possibilities circular polarization to
the right and circular polarization to
the left what's the difference between
saying it's a it's a linear
superposition of polarization States and
saying it has no angular momentum at all
it has equal probability for being
spinning to the right and spinning to
the left so doesn't that mean that it
has on the average no spin at all yes it
does mean that on the average it has no
spin but if you measure the angular
momentum of that Photon it will either
be right-handed or left-handed you will
never measure a photon which has no
angular momentum along that
direction so there are only two states
of the
photon and one other
point let's go back to uh to linear
polarization a photon moving down an
axis can be polarized here's the plane
perpendicular to the motion of the
photon if you send it through a plain
polarizer it can be be
polarized let's say along the Y AIS or
it can be polarized along the
x-axis the polarization is a vector but
it's a vector which is always
perpendicular to the direction of motion
of the photon it's always perpendicular
and the words for that are the
polarization is always
transverse there is no polarization of
the photon with a polarization where the
electric field Arrow points along the
direction of the photon
that's not allowed by Maxwell's
equations Maxwell's equations tell you
the electric and magnetic field and
therefore the polarization of the photon
are perpendicular to the direction of
motion so you can have two states of two
different polarizations you could call
it the X polarization state of the
photon or you could call it the Y
polarization state of the
photon neither of them is circular
polarization what about circular polar
ization circular polarization is a
linear superposition a quantum
mechanical linear
superposition
right-handed let's call it right- hand
polarization which means spin
right-handed that's equal to the state X
plus I * the state y
I no I won't say
it left-handed is x minus i y is it the
same like silver polarization like Stern
Gish experiment if you s i silver same
type of explanation for it doesn't have
anything to do with well it's just it's
just circular polarization just circular
polarization just pure circular
polarization circular polarization is a
Quantum linear super each Photon a
circularly polarized photon is a Quantum
superposition of a x polarized Photon
and a y polarized Photon let me let me
ask this supposing I didn't put the y i
here supposing I just considered x + y
what kind of photon would that
be that would be linearly polarized but
a 45° angle to the to the uh to the
axes Okay so
if all you were allowed to do is put
real numbers here you would make linear
polarization which could point in any
direction perpendicular to the direction
of motion of the photon but having eyes
available gives you something new it
gives you circular
polarization if you use as your basis of
states the circularly polarized
States instead of the linearly polarized
states there are only two of them so the
angular momentum of the photon is either
along the Axis or along the opposite to
the axis and there is no Photon which
has zero angular momentum along the
axis the same is true of gravitons
slightly
differently gravitons are spin two
objects if they were massive they would
have five states but gravitons only have
two states
they roughly
speaking and this is an analogy I want
you to keep in mind it's a good analogy
and we'll we'll draw on it a graviton
moving down the axis with maximal
angular momentum that means two units of
angular momentum moving along the
z-axis
is
mathematically the same as two photons
each with a uh
with one unit of angular momentum
imagine taking two photons sticking them
together letting them move down the
axis the angular momentum of the two of
them there could be various
possibilities they could both be
circulating in the right-handed sense
then the angular momentum would be two
units they could be both circulating to
the left the angular momentum would be
minus 2 units what you don't have is a
graviton which corresponds to a photon
of right polarization and left
polarization gravitons have only two
states maximal rotation in One Direction
maximum rotation in the other direction
and mathematically you
can think
of just having a pair of photons of
right-handed can multiply this by
another Photon of the same kind and
think of it as a graviton that would be
useful a useful way to think about spin
two by combining two spin
ones what's that can we use this analogy
only for one gra or can we do this with
other quantum numbers
well there's a whole field of study
which studies Fineman diagrams for
gravitons by thinking of them as roughly
speaking squares of finan diagrams for
spin one particle but mostly I think
it's trickery there's no real sense in
which a graviton is two photons it's
just for combining the spins that it's
useful I can't think of any other sense
in which it's uh particularly useful
there are no other quantum number what
other quantum numbers does a photon have
or
graviton doesn't have anything else has
momentum has momentum has energy and has
spin doesn't have charge doesn't have
Barrion number doesn't have anything
else well it doesn't have
a a jump in the Spectrum either so what
doesn't have a jump in the Spectrum
Photon has a continuous Spectrum right
potentially a photon of a given momentum
only has one value of the
energy right but you were saying that a
continuous spectrum is what
distinguishes something that is a
particle from something is
not continuous spectrum of rest
masses or if you like a continuous
Spectrum for a given
momentum the pot of uh the pot of
particles
with in moving inside not a pot but in a
in a container of some sort it doesn't
really have continuous Spectrum but it
has extremely dense Spectrum but what I
mean by that is if the entire pot is at
rest there are lots and lots of energy
levels okay certainly we can generate a
continuous Spectrum just by moving it
but I was speaking about the pot at rest
now photons it's true can't be at rest
so you can't quite use that definition
you use a different definition say for a
given momentum
uh
so
okay so now we know something about
harmonic oscillators we know something
about
spin and what I want to come to now is
the spectrum of strings the low-lying
spectrum of strings the low-lying
spectrum means the first few States
let's just remember that
energy in this formal analogy between
non-relativistic physics and
relativistic physics energy becomes not
MC squared not the mass but the square
of the
mass so when we speak about the energy
of a vibrating string and we add them
all up to find the total energy of the
vibrating string
it corresponds to the square of the mass
okay not the mass itself that's just
something to
remember okay what are the discrete
energy levels of the string and we're
talking uh a string at rest meaning to
say it's not moving in the perpendicular
Direction at all what are the energies
well we just say look it's just a
collection of harmonic oscillators let's
see what we can make the first state and
the lowest state is the state which is
annihilated that's the ground state by
all the annihilation
operators in other words it's just the
state the ground
state all the B's and all the A's all
the annihilation operators give
zero it's the state in which neither or
none of these oscillators are at all
excited what's the energy of that state
well if we were doing ordinary quantum
mechanical harmonic oscillators we might
say it's a half har Omega right that's
the ground state energy of a string but
let's um let's leave it open for a
minute let's not Prejudice the
answer uh let's leave it flexible for a
moment and call the mass squared now
this is what does this stand for this
does not stand for the
vacuum it is not empty space
it is the
unexcited oscillators it's a particle
it's a particle moving down the z-axis
but it's got It's in the ground state of
all of its oscillations I wouldn't say
it has no oscillations because every
harmonic oscillator has zero point
oscillations because of the uncertainty
principle there's some fluctuation but
every one of the oscillators as as quiet
as it can be consistent with quantum
mechanics so this thing is a particle
and I'm not going to begin by
prejudicing about what the mass of that
particle is I'm just going to call it m
squared whatever it happens to be this
is the energy of the ground
state
or the square of the mass of the ground
state and we don't know what it is yet
we don't have a tool yet for finding out
what it is but whatever it is when we ex
when we when we excite it we will
increase it by integer amounts of energy
so let's see how we can excite it what
the lowest energy excitation is what's
the cheapest thing in energy we can do
to it and the cheapest thing in energy
that we can do to it is to
apply the creation operators the raising
operators but the lowest
one
A1 remember each oscillator increases
the energy by in in
units and so if we want to consider the
lowest energy we want to hit it with the
with the oscillator of smallest
frequency the oscillator of smallest
frequency corresponds to n =
1 so we hit it with a sub one
what's the energy of that uh
State oh incidentally what is the energy
of that
state we've increased it by one unit
this one here indicates that the
frequency of that particular oscillator
is one unit the energy that you add is
one unit this is increased the energy of
the ground state by one unit so the
energy of this state is
whatever m squar is +
one nobody's asking me about units how
could I be talking about energy and
saying one unit one one unit one uh one
Jewel one horsep not horsepower
horsepower is power horsepower
second
uh what's the British unit of
uh oh a British thermal unit yeah maybe
it's one British thermal
unit well this seems pretty unlikely
doesn't it so what is this one what am I
talking about when I say
one we'll come we it's something we
better come back to we better come back
to units I hope by the end of the
evening we'll come back to units but in
some units in some appropriate units the
units that we've been
working uh the first excited state which
is a Daga one gives us one extra unit of
energy
now that's not the only state that has
one extra unit of energy is there
another one you can think of
B1 same
energy what about any linear combination
of
them if you take two igen vectors of a
of the energy and you superpose them it
gives you back another igen Vector with
the same
energy
okay so any linear combination of these
has the same energy now
what what are the
properties of these objects A and B in
particular I mean what are their
transformation properties when you
rotate the space we have an axis a
preferred axis I defined the preferred
axis I said boost the system up so that
it's moving like hell along the z-axis
but I still have
a rotation symmetry of the entire thing
about the axis that I boosted
things how do A and B transform under
those
rotations well you ask where they came
from they came from X and Y
we wrote that X was some sum involving
B's and no sorry A's and Y was some sum
involving B's what is X and Y X and Y
are components of a
vector that's what they are the position
they're components of a vector they
transform the components X and Y
transform like the components of a
two-dimensional vector
what about the A's the A's obviously
also transform as a vector A and B if
you were to rotate the coordinates would
transform into some a cosine theta plus
b sin Theta it would just rotate like a
two-dimensional Vector so these A's and
B's are
vectors that
means that you can consider these two
things to have a vectorial character
this one is
pointing they're always in the plane
perpendicular to the to the motion
always in the plane perpendicular to the
motion uh which
is
large this one has some kind of
vectorial property in the One
Direction this one has vectorial
property in the two direction
so these two states transform into each
other as
vectors they have the same properties as
the plain polarization of
photons the photon polarization is also
a vector namely it corresponds to the
direction of the electric field at some
at some instant it's a vector it points
in the direction perpendicular to the
motion of the phot
and so it's looking as if these two
things must correspond
somehow to a vector character to the
particle how would can we turn it into a
circular polarization yes we can turn it
into a circular polarization instead of
taking A1 or B1 we take A1 Plus
ib1 and that's circularly polarized
something it's a string which has the
properties of a circularly polarized the
particle and of course we can put minus
there and the mathematics of it
is identical to the
mathematics of the polarization states
of a particle moving down the axis they
transform into each other in the
rotations we could linearly superpose
these with real
coefficients and then we would just be
rotating the direction of uh of um
oscillation or we can add them with an i
and we turn them into circularly po now
this is not not easy to visualize don't
try to visualize it it's the
transformation properties which
count notice that there is not a third
state with the same
energy there is no other third
oscillator
there's only the X oscillator the Y
oscillator and that's it there is no
third state so there is no third
polarization State there's only one
conclusion which is consistent with
lenen variance with
relativity with the properties of these
things this object these two objects
must be
massless they must be like the massless
photon if there are only two
polarization States
that would not be consistent with a
massive particle because a massive
particle you can bring to rest and turn
its direction of
motion and create the third polarization
state so these two things these two
states behave exactly like the two
polarization states of the photon they
moving down the axis let's not give them
any motion perpendicular to the axis no
overall motion moving down the a axis
and there are two polarization
States they do have the
properties of the polarization states of
photons a vector character to them in
the perpendicular Direction other words
they're transversely polarize
things they are identified as photonik
objects in string
theory uh and they must be massless if
they're not massless there something
deeply wrong lenen variance cannot be
maintained and uh so we
come you must Realize by now we've come
to a disaster we've come to a very
unfortunate uh
crash where at this point we should
throw away String Theory why because m^
2 + 1 has to be
zero the mass of this object which is
not the ground state it's been excited
by one unit as this
if it's to make sense as a relativistic
object it has to be massless and that
means m squ is negative okay big deal
who cares if m squ is
negative the problem with that is M
squar was the energy or the mass the
mass squared of the ground state without
these a1s in other words the string
which was not vibrating along the x or y
AIS the ground state of the
string that's intolerable having a
particle with negative Mass squared is
crazy Mass squared is positive how can
Mass squ be
negative you're going imaginary Mass
right okay H r0 rotate what by 90
degrees and in what
space negative mass squ is a bad thing
okay imaginary negative Mass squared
imaginary mass is a bad thing so let me
tell see why is it a bad thing so what
you've discovered something that a
certain parameter is negative what does
it
mean all right an object with negative
mass square has a name you know the
name
Aion tach
on the tacky comes from the
same it's it's not that it's a tacky
particle I mean that's not the point it
is tacky but
uh what's the what's the thing in your
car which tells you how fast the engine
is going tach tachometer tachometer
tachometer yeah uh tacki Taki is either
I guess it's a Greek
word t tacher yeah yeah but T I think
tacki I think refers to speed
speed I think it I think it's a word for
speed and what's
that no I don't think so I I don't think
so I think it could be linear speed too
I don't know I don't know my Greek and I
don't even know if it's a Greek word
maybe it's a Yiddish word I don't know
but it does it does it does but I think
I think it I think the prefix tacky
refers to speed in general I don't know
for sure but I do know where the why
they called it attach on aach on meant
that it moves very fast in fact so fast
that it moves faster than the speed of
light now that's clearly something bad
okay Einstein told us there are nothing
that can move faster than the speed of
light so we seem to have encountered
something which is a tachon with
negative Mass
squared let me tell maybe I should stop
at this point and tell you a little bit
about tacons they're bad we want to get
rid of them they they're
intolerable And if every string Theory
had a tachon you would not have heard of
string theory it would have been
abandoned sometime around
1969 and you would never have heard
about it again so of course the answer
is that there are many string theories
many good string theories that do not
have the
tachon okay there are no string theories
that don't have this Photon like object
this is a good thing because the world
has photons and it doesn't have tach on
but let me just tell you you about
tachon a little bit and how physicists
use the terminology today only crackpots
think that they move faster than the
speed of
light okay so don't fall into that
trap or that they can somehow send
signals faster than the speed of light
that's not the measure the issue here
but let me show you why there was some
idea that they exceeded the speed of
light uh
the
important quantity of interest for the
moment now is the frequency of a
wave versus its wave
number what is the frequency of a
um for nonre or which is equivalent of
course it's of course equivalent to the
energy of an object apart from a factor
of H bar it's the same as the energy as
a function of the
momentum so let's uh let's write that
down for an ordinary non-relativistic
particle e of p is p^2 over 2 m
right I'll just point something out to
you we could uh we could uh prove
something about this but the derivative
of e with respect to P what is that
p over M and P over m
is the
velocity that's a general rule it's
actually a property of waves If instead
of e you put Omega and instead of P you
put k then it's a property of waves that
the group velocity is given by the
derivative of the frequency with respect
to the wave number or the energy with
respect to the momentum let's try it out
for something else how about in
relativity what's E versus p
let's start with a
photon is it eal P * C or eal p over
c p * C right yeah e is equal to P * C
what is the derivative of e with respect
to
P which is of course the velocity of a
photon all right let's try it a little
more generally e = the square TK of P ^2
+
m^2 okay now it gets a little hard
derivative of e with respect to
P that gives us 1 / by
twice the square < TK of p^2 +
m^2 and then what's in the numerator 2
p okay so it's p
over P ^2 + m^2 sorry p over p^2 +
m^2 okay I'm not going to try to
convince you that this is the velocity
of a relativistic particle but it does
have one property notice that it's less
than
one square < TK of p^2 + m^2 is bigger
P okay square root of p^2 + M2 is bigger
than the square root of just P ^2 so P /
this is always less than
one that another way of seeing that
relativistic particles always move with
speed less than than the speed of light
what if there was a minus
here goes faster than the speed of light
that's why people call these things
tachon
when somebody or other and I have no
idea who it was first decided that it
might be interesting to think about
particles that moves faster than the
speed of light they postulated and they
ative Mass squared okay the question is
what is really wrong with that other
than it seems to contradict something
that uh that Einstein taught
us what does a tachon really mean and
the answer is it doesn't mean something
moving or that sends transmits signals
faster than speed of light it means that
that the vacuum is
unstable it means that something can
happen that can
destabilize the system that's the usual
source of tachon so I'm going to give
you I'm going to give you an example but
first let's think about wave equations
let's start with wave
equations these equations are also ways
of thinking about wave equations here's
a wave equation
that's an ordinary wave equation for as
a function uh let's uh yeah let's read
it this way
okay what kind of wave is that does it
what does it move with speed of
what d by dt^ 2
stands for Omega squared
right we've done this before we've done
this many times if you have a wave the
time derivative each time derivative
gives you a factor of
Omega what about each space
derivative K right each space derivative
gives you a k so this equation says that
Omega s equal
k^2 or Omega equals
K I've left out the speed of light I've
set the speed of light equal to one
so what's the velocity of this wave the
Omega
Decay one okay how do I turn it into
something that moves slower than the
speed of light what do I
add if I want to add a mass
term here it is we
have
yeah which side can you figure that out
is it this way no it's minus this way
it's
minus minus m^2
5 then we would have incidentally is is
the derivative with respect to T is that
Omega or I
Omega I Omega right if we have something
that goes as e to the I Omega T and we
differentiate it it gives us an i Omega
so so this gives us this is really
another way of talking about minus Omega
2 this is minus k^
2 and this is minus
m^2 right which is the same as Omega s =
k^2 + m^2 this one
here so this is what you do to
um what does this correspond to in the
in the energy you remember what it
corresponds to in the energy of the
wave the energy of the wave
has d by dt^
2 12 it has plus d by
dx2 and this gives us plus m^2 5^ 2
does anybody remember this from last
quarter wave equations and the mass term
oops how you put in a Mass for a
particle in terms of the wave equations
Klein Gordon equations with mass this
was the
rule now
notice
that imagine what is this this is a kind
of potential energy for the field notice
that it's
positive it's positive if the mass is
positive that
means that if you increase
fi the energy
increases the result of that is if you
increase
fi it will oscillate back it's just like
a harmonic oscillator a positive energy
when you displace the field a little
bit and because you gain some energy or
it costs some energy because it costs
some potential energy to increase fi
it'll swing back and the wave will
oscillate what would happen if you had a
negative term here so that the potential
energy of fi looked like
that you fall off the
cliff you fall off the
cliff
you so it's an instability it's an
instability of the vacuum the if you
thought that the vacuum was just 5
equals 0 and you gave it a little push
down you would
go here's a kind of interesting question
supposing you really did
start with Fi very carefully
balanced at the top of the potential
everywhere everywhere in space fire was
absolutely balanced at the at the top
well it would sit that way forever if it
were absolutely
balanced it would be like a you know a
sharp pencil perfectly balanced you give
it a push the tiniest push and off it
goes but um supposing you pushed it only
at one point right you want a model for
this tell can we make a model for yeah I
can make a model for it here's a model
for it to think about you have a bunch
of vertical
pendulums and they're coupled together
by
Springs they're in a gravitational
field if you set them all up perfectly
vertically they will stay that
way if you only had a single pendulum
and you gave it a little push what would
happen in fact it wouldn't it wouldn't
fly off to Infinity but it would make a
big deviation from where it started so
the starting point was
unstable what happens if you push all of
them
simultaneously well you know what
happens they all go flying over the top
but here's an interesting question
supposing you pushed one of them only
one of them this one right over here how
fast would the um would the signal
propagate outward you push one of them
it pushes the next one it pushes the
next one and sure enough if you wait
they all go flopping over but how fast
does that signal spread out speed of
sound which is a well we're thinking
about light being uh the the velocity of
waves does it go faster than the speed
of light the way the tachon suggests it
might doesn't it doesn't that the
falling over the domino effect
proceeds with the edge or the you know
the outer boundary the outer envelope of
the um of the domino effect will spread
out no faster than the speed of light so
the conclusion is that tach on are not
to be thought of as things that go
faster than the speed of light string
theory has not provided a way of
exceeding the speed of light what it's
done is it's given us a theory with an
unstable ground with an unstable vacuum
a little tiny push will destabilize the
whole world that's not a good thing
that's something that we need to avoid
and that's where super String Theory
comes
in that's why we need it uh that's why
we have to do better than just this very
simple string theory that I've described
but okay so far what we found if we
ignore the
tachon just say somehow by Magic we're
going to get rid of it we have found a
theory which has a photon like object in
it a massless photon likee object with
two polarization
States and it's a candidate for
something like the
photon I said to you that there are
tricks and ways of getting rid of the
tachon you might ask me are there tricks
and ways of getting rid of the
photon-like object the massless thing
well the answer is nobody ever found one
within uh within months of the discovery
of string Theory people had figured out
how to get rid of the
tachon they never got rid of the
photonik object why might they have
liked to get rid of the photon like
object massless spin one
particle why not why it sounds like a
good thing it could be the
photon the reason was at the time string
theory was not supposed to be a theory
of photons it was supposed to be a
theory of hadrons mesons barons
and there is no
massless Meson there are no massless
Meson so this was thought to be a wart
not a
feature at the time people wanted to get
rid of not only the tachon but also the
massless photon like object in all the
years that people have been doing String
Theory the tachon was very easy to get
rid of and nobody ever got rid of the
the spin one object the the
photon yeah is this the one that Ed is
comes out of strength area the graviton
no this is not the graviton yet this so
far is the
photon or a to call it the
photon would be a little bit
misleading uh there are many sources of
a photon likee object in string theory
which one is the real Photon and what do
we do with all the others those are very
model dependent those depend on details
to say that this is the Photon would be
misleading uh it is a photon like object
it is a gauge Bon it is a thing which
behaves like a photon in many
ways uh and we'll need to come back to
it but I just show you
this let's uh should
we summarize of right right now if you
develop it you have a m s less than zero
which is the tan and that's not allowed
not allow and we're not yet at the point
where we know how to get rid of it I
wouldn't say so
much from a strictly uh theoretical
point of
view quantum mechanics with an upside
down potential is perfectly good there's
nothing wrong with it it just doesn't
have a ground state and that's bad yeah
so it doesn't look like the
world now course
yeah good enough in this case here we
know what would happen to these guys
they would just turn over and I wind up
oscillating about the
bottom okay here who knows if there's a
bottom
yeah to get the gravitons we have to
study something new but something new is
closed strings so far these are open
strings open strings means they have two
ends ends so
period it's hard to have a string with
one
end unless you're a
Buddhist never
mind a Zen
Buddhist I apologize T he's done
Buddhist in the class with um I it seems
that you're looking at the property
properties of photons with polarization
and the properties of these strings
and as far as that goes it matches up
are there other properties of photons
and other properties of strings that
also match absolutely
absolutely
um yeah the interesting questions would
have to do with the radiation of
photons now to have a radiation of
photons you have to have objects which
carry charge
we haven't yet discussed what kind of
objects might correspond to the things
which carry
charge but once if we found string if we
found string objects which played the
role of charges we could ask if we knew
the rules and we're going to talk about
the rules we could ask about the rules
of emission of photons by accelerated
charges and the answer is yes we would
find out that they behave exactly the
same way that
um that emission of photons from charged
particles
Works definite rules definite rules
definite probability distributions
definite radiation
patterns uh and those patterns would be
reproduced quite uh quite
precisely so
yeah okay let's uh
let's move on I think I mentioned this
last time
but tell you
anyway the basic process of interaction
that takes place so far we're talking
about free strings free strings means an
isolated string moving by itself
unaccompanied by any other and doing
nothing except uh propagating along some
axis and doing its own internal
Wiggles but its Wiggles the
manifestations of its Wiggles are simply
a colle a discrete collection of energy
levels and also angular
momentum uh string can move internally
in many ways for example one of the ways
it can
move remember these strings the
mathematics of them is the mathematics
of non-relativistic strings one of the
things a string can do is it can
rotate about an axis rotate like a
dumbbell about an axis the centrifical
force being the thing which stretches it
out so this must be something that these
relativistic strings can do this means
that they can have all sorts of angular
momenta not just one unit of angular
momentum or two units of angular
momentum but you can spin them
up but when you do
course we're doing quantum mechanics
each unit of angular momentum cost you
an additional unit of energy can you
have pitch pole rotation can you have
what pitch pole rotation what's a pitch
pole rotation like one of them stays
pitch and the other no that's not
possible no they'll rotate about the
center of
mass
right
uh any system when it's
rotating will rotate about its Center of
mass
so the question is where's the center of
mass and if it's a nice straight string
like this rotating about an axis of
course the center of mass would be at
the center
so
uh of course if you had something to
Anchor the end of the string to then it
could string swing around that a that
anchor and there are anchors in string
theory but it swing around energy level
of a atom can it
like the photons holding the electrons
to the center of the atom can it pit
pole out from that you're asking whether
an electron can circulate around a
nucleus electron circulates around a
nucleus the reason the reason that the
electron circulates around the nucleus
with the nucleus standing still is
because the nucleus is very heavy so the
center really strictly speaking they
both rotate about a Common Center of
Mass but because the nucleus is a couple
of thousand times heavier than the
electron it looks like the nucleus is
not moving
okay um what did you call this pitch
pole pitch pole pitch poing where where
you pull this in fixed and this end
rotates to gets thrown out just like the
Scottish do with the big logs P oh yes
no I don't
know I thought it was the Jews who
invented
that I was the
Russians
yes okay the basic process of
interaction that allows strings to talk
to each other to interact with each
other to do things I think I discussed
this last time but I'll tell you what it
is we're not going to do anything
mathematical with it tonight we will try
to describe this a little bit
mathematically later but just
qualitatively the things that
happen particularly to these open
strings is very simple it's really the
only process everything is built out of
it and uh we're going to find even a
simpler description but at the moment
this is very simple
the only thing that happens apart from
these strings wiggling and doing their
own thing the only thing that allows
them to talk to each other is that when
end points find themselves at coincident
points in space in other words when they
touch there is a
probability or let's call it an
amplitude for them to join
that's called a joining
interaction so there is some probability
they don't inevitably do it there is a
constant in the theory it's called the
string coupling constant and what it
does is it takes a pair of
strings here's a pair of strings moving
along in space time upward is
time there's a
string here comes another
string their end points meet at this
point and they joined together to form a
single
string that's the
analog in string theory of what in
Quantum field theory is the vertex where
two particles come together and join and
make a third
particle this could be a electron and an
electron and a photon or it could be any
of the other interactions that we've
studied two particles come together join
and make a third particle two strings
come together and join and make a third
string but the process is very simple it
doesn't just happen any old way it
happens by the end points coming
together touching
and combining to form a single string
now anything that can happen in quantum
mechanics can unhappen meaning to say
that quantum mechanics is a reversible
Theory anything that can happen in time
in One Direction can happen the opposite
way in
time so that means that there is also an
amplitude for a single string to
break and form
ends if that probability were
large the string would have very little
Integrity it would constantly be
breaking
up if that probability is very small
then the string might last a long time
and uh before it breaks up like that so
uh one of the assumptions in string
theory is that this probability is small
the probability is called the string
coupling constant I think I said that
and it's the analog of the constant of
nature which would be what would it be
for the electron electron
Photon it would be the electric charge
it would be the fine structure constant
right it would be the square of the
electric charge that probability
probabilities are squares of
amplitudes uh so the probability for two
strings to join is like the electric
charge but it's the same it's quite
independent of which kinds of strings
are joining in the sense that they could
be the excited strings they could be the
rotating strings they could be the
vibrating strings there's some
probability when two two end points
touch each other that they fuse
and that same
probability that if the string is just
moving along minding its own business
that a that what's the opposite of
fuse
fish
right it can fuse or it can fish
break break anyway along its length uh
and those
are all right
so this is the basic structure but one
of the things that can happen happen is
just like a snake which encounters its
own tail and it's too stupid to know
that it's found its own tail might bite
its own tail the same thing can happen
with strings they're also rather
stupid and if the string happens to come
around like that it's in the course of
its Evolution it might just do that and
when it does the head detects a tail and
guess what
happens they join
so it's inevitable there is no way
around it that if you have a theory of
open strings and those open strings
interact in other words have this
joining and uh
splitting process happening then it is
quite inevitable that the same theory
has to have closed
strings closed strings are
unavoidable can you have a theory with
closed we're going to work out the
mathematic matics of closed strings I
don't think we're going to do it tonight
we'll work out the ma the mathematics of
closed strings is very similar to open
strings we'll work it
out question when you have these fish
and infusion situations does that change
the energy state of the Str
yeah yes it does does the theory say
have yes absolutely it
does uh but for our purposes now I just
wanted to motivate for you why closed
strings are inevitable in a theory of
strings or in a theory of interacting
strings now what about a theory of
closed strings that abono starts with
closed
strings is it inevitable that there will
always be open
strings
no
no I mean I don't I
agree doesn't make sense to me to have
to be doesn't make sense that they would
have to be but then you can ask all
right but then how do closed strings
interact with each other if they don't
interact by splitting and then touching
other strings and the way they interact
is different they interact here's two
closed
strings and they come
together and then fuse to form another
closed string at no point did they ever
form open strings they came together
like this touch and formed another
closed string so the answer is it is
quite possible to have theories of pure
closed
strings with no open strings but it is
not possible to have a theory of open
strings without closed
strings that's interesting it means that
a prediction of string
theory is that there are closed strings
it is not a prediction of string theory
that there will exist open strings
strings it is a prediction of string
theory that there must exist closed
strings just because there can be closed
there can be open string theories no
they can be closed string theories
without open
strings what do you think the uh the
close if the open string if
the interesting uh low expectation of an
open string is a photon what do you
think the interesting excitation lowest
excitation of a closed string is
Al the graviton the graviton and so one
of the thing one of the things that
string
theory literally predicts because you
can't not have it is
gravity there are many many string
theories that have things like
electromagnetism but some of them don't
but there is no string theory that
doesn't have gravity every string theory
necessarily has gravity just because it
will have
I I never heard of a string theory that
didn't have closed strings it got to
have some kind of strings why is this to
closed string necessarily gravity ah
well no that's what we're going to come
to why was the open string necessarily
photons well we did some manipulations
and found out it was the only
interpretation we'll do the same thing
exactly the same thing with Clos
strings exactly the same thing I don't
think we have time tonight can an open
string convert a closed string into an
open one
if in some string
theories the rules involve the splitting
and joining process in those string
theories a closed string can become an
open
string but there are also string
theories that don't have this particular
process of breaking like this well if
they do have open strings will that will
that also be possible which which if if
you have a string theory that has both
open and closed then can a closed one be
interact with an open one such that it
becomes open yeah there's a number of
ways that a closed string can interact
with an open string but the simplest is
the following
once you have closed strings in
fact once you have them this is even
implicit in open String Theory you can
have the basic thing that can happen is
two ends can touch and join but there's
something else that can happen the other
thing that can happen is two strings can
touch at a point which is not an end and
then they can rearrange
all right so let's see what we started
with we started with two strings did we
start with two or one yeah we started
with
two this way and this became
this again it's the same process where
two things come in touch and then
rearrange all right that's a process
that can happen in string theory I I
will have to prove to you that can
happen I'm telling you now okay so let's
see what happens if you have a closed
and open string if you have a closed and
open
string the closed string here's the
closed
string the simplest thing that can
happen is the closed string can
come touch the open string
rearrange and now what is it
formed one big open
string okay so let's think about what
that means means that means an open
string is moving along to begin
with let's draw it here's our open
string a closed string comes along
closed and what's left over at the
end
open that process will turn into the
absorpt ion of a
graviton by a particle which is not a
graviton right so here's something we
found out closed strings can absorb
gravitons same way open strings can
absorb
gravitons in fact everything can absorb
a graviton that inst string theory is
why everything
gravitates in essence and in a
simple-minded way the fact that an open
string or a closed string can always
absorb a graviton by this process is the
UL well
is one of the ways of thinking about the
universality of
gravitation uh do we ever get into
locking closed Loops do we ever get into
locking closed Loops say it again oh
yeah well okay we should talk about that
um in weekly couple String Theory where
the interaction is weak the strings are
transparent to each other but they can
do this but with a with a small
probability with a small probability
they come along and they do that but
they can also pass right through each
other so these strings are
not obstacles like shoelaces that they
can't pass through each other they can
pass through ah yeah yeah they can pass
through each
other uh I'll bring you a super string
next time and I'll show you how uh how
it uh how it works remind me somebody
tell send me an email to bring a super
string in and I'll show you what uh what
what it can do so it's already have no
no I'll bring you a real one so you said
the joining amplitude was kind of
independent of the state of the string
yeah and just I if I had something
spinning really fast then you might
anticipate that it has a higher
probability of is that just a choice in
the theory or is there some reason why
that doesn't work no
no the basic probability per unit
time if they're
touching to interact is the same for all
strings but keep in mind if they're
moving fast they spend less time uh near
each other so if the probability per
unit
time is the same if they're moving past
each other fast there will be less of a
probability of them
joining right so it's it's it's
basically a probability per unit time
that's uh you when you're showing these
strings you know you got smaller ones
you got bigger ones right is there
fundamental characteristic of like mass
or energy or something that represents
that length Okay so the first thing we
should take up next time is units I
think that's what you're asking me about
is there a unit right now there must be
a unit because I've done all sorts of
equations which didn't really make
dimensional
sense what is what is X x is a length
right so it must have units of length
what about a creation and Annihilation
operator well they have commutation
relations a a dagger is equal to
one so what's the dimension of
a h no units so how can X be
proportional to a there's some missing
units in the in the story uh frequencies
what's the units of
frequencies inverse time but my
frequencies are integers integers don't
have any units there's some missing
units that I haven't put in
here and I think the first thing we want
to talk about next time is units what
units another way to ask the question
is I tell you
that adding an excitation of energy
increases the mass or the mass squared
by a certain amount in what
units Mass that's what we were saying
before in what units in kilograms in uh
in Gig electron volts in slugs what unit
does there's one unit of excitation how
much does it increase the mass by
what answer would you
guess Mass no that's too in a
fundamental theory of gravity you might
think it's the plunk Mass you might too
big that's too big though it is too big
yeah so we're going to find it's a
little smaller than the plunk Mass but
uh that's uh that's something next time
we will take up explicitly the issue of
units and uh which just clearly
important it's important
yeah within Quant theory is coupling
constant the same or can strings have
different hands and different
probability of of joining in the
simplest String Theory it's just a
single constant and uh and generally
it's a single
constant
uh
um yeah in fact really strictly speaking
there are no constants in string theory
but uh we we'll get to that um before we
beat this uh sex of strings to death um
there's this open and there's the close
is the possibility of a string splitting
on its
own uh splitting means breaking but not
separating oh mean like a y h like a y
like single splitting but not split
lengthwise I think I know what
lengthwise
no no that is that is not not allowed to
split split hairs you're
not you're not allowed to split hairs
right right going an end to a midpoint I
think you're asking whether you can have
a more complicated
object like
this now this doesn't correspond to a
Fineman diagram it corresponds to three
strings joined at a at a Vertex at the
center is that what you're asking yeah
that they're a string theories that do
have that possibility there's a there's
an enormous variety of different string
theories the question is what do they
all have in common if you ask what is
the generic prediction of string theory
then you're really asking what do they
all have in common and the only thing
that I can really think of that they all
have in common is they all have closed
strings and they all have
gravitons some versions have open
strings other versions have I call this
a bolo uh uh you know what a bolo is
Argentinian Cowboy swings it around and
and Tangles uh and Tangles his feet in
it and falls over and falls on his face
and
right uh yeah in fact in hron physics
remember hron physics is a version of
string
theory when we talk about units next
time I will tell you the difference
between String Theory as a but the
theory of hadrons do you know what this
kind of thing would
be versus this kind of
thing quk could it three
quarks be three
quarks
barion this would be a quark and an
antiquark right so so yes string
theories can have these kind of things
but the one thing they always have is
the Clos strings
do the coupling constants change uh
depending on the dimension of
interaction for the strings as
well you're I'm not sure what the
question is the coupling if the strings
are colliding in one dimension Black
Water we have another dimension the
string coupling constants will change as
well
yes yes um there is a dimensional by
dimensional I mean the number of
dimensions of space there is
a story about the values of the coupling
constants as a function of Dimensions
yes there is but we'll take that as we
come to
it one more question I got I want to go
home but uh
yeah I missed the first 15 minutes so
you may have already answered but when
they're moving uh and they combine and
break what is the I mean is it the grav
gra gravity that is making them move or
no
charge no um think Newton think Newton
for a minute is it gravity that makes
things move no it's inertia that makes
things move once they start
moving uh it was it was Aristotle who
said there has to be a cause for motion
it was nton who said nonsense things if
you set them in motion will keep moving
strings are the same it's not gravity
which makes things move what does
gravity do gravity causes things to
accelerate so we haven't gotten to
gravity yet and where gravity comes
from uh so far this is a theory which we
have no particular reason up till now to
have any gravity in
it what makes things move in
general forces and
acceleration
CV inertia keeps them moving what starts
them moving
an exchange of momentum with another
particle
possibly I think you have to think about
that supposing something weren't
moving now you look at it from another
frame of reference it is moving so what
made it
move changing your point of reference
changing your point of refence if you
have a system you have the energy of the
whole system which is divided among the
the particles but all I'm telling you is
even if a thing is not moving in one
frame of reference it is moving in
another frame of
reference so even Galileo understood
that so Galileo knew enough not to ask
the question what causes motion but to
ask the question what causes changes of
motion and that's forces forces C cause
changes of motion so
um H quum fluctuate well in classical
mechanics Force cause change of motion
right what causes the motion in the
first place
well initial
conditions initial conditions what
caused the initial
conditions Woody
Allen for more please visit us at
stanford.edu